Hey boker tov בוקר טוב boker tov everybody. Today's daf דף daf
is 61 samech alef ס"א. samech alef. We're a little behind. We
pick up on samech amud bet ס"ב samech amud bet right after
the mishna משנה. mishna. We're now switching to Avodah Zarah עבודה זרה
Avodah Zarah which is one of the cases of sekilah סקילה sekilah
and in particular we mentioned
the
act of avodah עבודה. avodah. Interesting in the act of avodah עבודה
avodah is also accepting that other god as a god. That that's
considered an avodah's עבודה's avodah interesting. You might have said that's lo
yihiyeh lecha elohim acherim לא יהיה לך אלוהים אחרים lo yihiyeh lecha
elohim acherim but not an actual avodah עבודה. avodah. And we have
the fact avodahs עבודהs avodah mentioned as the generic ovedet עובדת ovedet
which we'll see in the Gemara גמרא Gemara means its classic form
of avodah עבודה. avodah. What the worshippers consider to be the classic
form and also the things that are
classic you
know throughout various forms of worship and certainly classic in the Beit
HaMikdash בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash so that's slaughtering, burning on the altar,
libations, and the Gemara גמרא Gemara will include in libations sprinkling of
blood and prostration. Okay so slaughtering? Mezabeiach
מזבח.
mezabeiach. It's not like putting it on it's not putting it on.
No no zoveiach זובח zoveiach is how it appears elsewhere. Okay so
maktir מקטיר maktir is putting it on the altar. Alright so the
Gemara גמרא Gemara says like this: Mai echad ha-oved מאי אחד העובד?
Mai echad ha-oved? So what does it mean whether you worship it?
It lists all the forms of worship. So Amar Rabbi Yirmiyah hachi
ka'amar אמר רבי ירמיה הכי קאמר. Amar Rabbi Yirmiyah hachi ka'amar. This
is what it means. Echad ha-oved kedarkah ve-echad ha-mezabeiach ve-echad ha-maktir ve-echad
ha-menaseiach ve-echad ha-mishtachaveh אחד העובד כדרכה ואחד המזבח ואחד המקטיר ואחד המנסך
ואחד המשתחוה. Echad ha-oved kedarkah ve-echad ha-mezabeiach ve-echad ha-maktir ve-echad ha-menaseiach ve-echad
ha-mishtachaveh. Whether you do the classic form or whether you do any
of these four even if it's not classic form. Va-afilu shelo kedarkah
ואפילו שלא כדרכה Va-afilu shelo kedarkah even if that's not the normal
way. Velichshov nami zorek ולחשוב נמי זורק Velichshov nami zorek so what
about the throwing of the blood? Amar Abaye zorek hainu menaseiach אמר
אביי זורק היינו מנסך. Amar Abaye zorek hainu menaseiach. That's included in
the phrase of to do a libation. So it's putting some liquid
on the altar. Of course conceptually it's very different. You know the
libation is the offering of the wine whereas the throwing of the
blood is the offering of the animal as it were but anyway
that's what it's meant to be included here. Dechtiv דכתיב Dechtiv as
the verse says kol bal asich niskeihem midam כל בל אסיך נסכיהם
מדם kol bal asich niskeihem midam lest I give their libations of
blood. Fine. So that's in terms of meaning of the mishna משנה.
mishna. So we got the classic form and we got these four.
Minani milei מנא הני מילי? Minani milei? Where's this from? Detanu rabanan
דתנו רבנן Detanu rabanan our rabbis taught: Ilu ne'emar zoveiach yechoram אילו
נאמר זובח יחרם Ilu ne'emar zoveiach yechoram one who slaughters shall be
put under the ban and the ban here understanding to mean the
death penalty. Hayiti omer bezoveiach kodshim bachutz hakatuv medaber הייתי אומר בזובח
קדשים בחוץ הכתוב מדבר. Hayiti omer bezoveiach kodshim bachutz hakatuv medaber. Talking
about just slaughtering sacrifices outside of the Beit HaMikdash בית המקדש. Beit
HaMikdash. I mean the end of the pasuk פסוק pasuk is... the
pasuk פסוק pasuk is zoveiach lelohim yechoram זובח לאלוהים יחרם zoveiach lelohim
yechoram one who slaughters to other gods here it's assumed Elohim אלוהים
Elohim means other gods. Bilti l'Hashem levado בלתי לה' לבדו Bilti l'Hashem
levado except only to God. So if it didn't have the word
lelohim לאלוהים lelohim maybe it would have meant outside of the Beit
HaMikdash בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash as opposed to in the Beit HaMikdash
בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Talmud lomar lelohim תלמוד לומר לאלוהים. Talmud lomar
lelohim. Bezoveiach la'avodat kochavim hakatuv medaber בזובח לעבודת כוכבים הכתוב מדבר. Bezoveiach
la'avodat kochavim hakatuv medaber. Talking that you slaughter the animal to other
gods. Ein li ela bezoveiach אין לי אלא בזובח. Ein li ela
bezoveiach. I only know slaughtering. Maktir menaseiach minayin מקטיר מנסך מנין? Maktir
menaseiach minayin? How do I know burning things on the altar which
would include the fats of the sacrifice and libations which would include
the blood? Talmud lomar bilti l'Hashem levado תלמוד לומר בלתי לה' לבדו.
Talmud lomar bilti l'Hashem levado. It only these worships are only for
God.
Bilti l'Hashem levado בלתי לה' לבדו. Bilti l'Hashem levado. So rikan ha-avodot
kulan leshem hameyuchad ריקן העבודות כולן לשם המיוחד. rikan ha-avodot kulan leshem
hameyuchad. All of the worships have been emptied out to God. So
meaning all the classic forms of worship in the Beit HaMikdash בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash are designated only for God and are included in
this source I know and included in this verse as under the
prohibition of avodah zarah עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Now Rashi רש"י Rashi
says but if you think about it the classic forms of avodah
עבודה avodah in the Beit HaMikdash בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash is shechitah
שחיטה shechitah kabbalat hadam קבלת הדם kabbalat hadam holachat hadam הולכת הדם
holachat hadam and zerikat hadam זריקת הדם. zerikat hadam. So what happened
to kabbalah קבלה kabbalah and holachah הולכה? holachah? So Rashi רש"י Rashi
says well there's no pesukim פסוקים pesukim we ever find by avodah
zarah עבודה זרה avodah zarah emphasize those as worships of avodah zarah
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. But the other things Rashi רש"י Rashi quotes
various pesukim פסוקים pesukim are identified also as worships of avodah zarah
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So it's not really just the classic avodot
עבודות. avodot. Okay like nisuei... to be menaseiach מנסך menaseiach to do
a libation it's true you do that in the Beit HaMikdash בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash but you know we know that much more from
the world of like stam yeinam סתם יינם stam yeinam and yayin
nesech יין נסך yayin nesech that it's a worship of avodah zarah
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So Rashi רש"י Rashi actually says that it's
an intersection of classic forms of avodah עבודה avodah in the Beit
HaMikdash בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash that we know from other pesukim פסוקים
pesukim are also classic forms of worship of avodah zarah עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah. And once you have those then it's an act of
avodah zarah עבודה זרה avodah zarah even if for this idol or
for this god it is not seen as a natural form of
worship.
Okay what about the say holachah הולכה? holachah?
What? He just says we never find... it would be a lav
לאו lav but you wouldn't be chayiv misah חייב מיתה.
chayiv misah. Okay and it makes sense because holachah הולכה holachah for
us is more of a preparatory step.
Right I mean that's true right exactly. Meaning even for us when
we call it one of the four avodot עבודות avodot it's strange
it's not an actual... but of course shechitah שחיטה shechitah also you
could say is not actually the worship itself whereas for here it's
a classic form of you know classic shechutei chutz שחוטי חוץ shechutei
chutz also and so on. Okay so it says like this now.
Lefi she-yatzas zvichah lidon ba'avodat pnim לפי שיצאת זביחה לידון בעבודת פנים.
Lefi she-yatzas zvichah lidon ba'avodat pnim. Okay so now because zvichah זביחה
zvichah is unique that it's a worship that is done inside the
Beit HaMikdash בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and therefore we learn anything like
this. So the Gemara
גמרא Gemara says: minayin lerabot hishtachavah מנין לרבות השתחוה? minayin lerabot hishtachavah?
How do you know prostration which is not a... particular worship in
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and he says יבוא כל בשר להשתחוות,
yavo chol basar l'hishtachavos, but nevertheless ולפני, uv'phanay, I understand, but nevertheless
in terms of the classic הלכה, halacha, it is not an exact
form of worship in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
Oh, I see. Oh, meaning it's not a form of worship, but
it is done in the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash?
No, okay, there's a פסוק pasuk in ישעיהו: Yeshayahu: יבוא כל בשר
להשתחוות לפני. yavo chol basar l'hishtachavos l'fanai. It's not anywhere else, you
know, in תנ״ך. Tanach. Go ahead, you're looking about what you do
in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. השתחוואה hishtachavah is not classic, okay?
So it's not a classic form of עבודה avoda in the—it's a
form of עבודה avoda in the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. So your claim is that that's a פסוק pasuk for
now?
No, yeah, yeah, correct. So anyway, it's a form of worship of
God, but it's not a form of worship in the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. So מניין לרבות השתחוואה? minayin l'rabos hishtachavah? תלמוד לומר: talmud
lomar: וילך ויעבד אלוהים אחרים וישתחו להם. vayelech vaya'avod elohim acherim vayishtachu
lahem. Okay, so no, we learn it from another פסוק pasuk that
speaks also that a form of עבודה avoda is prostrating, השתחוואה. hishtachavah.
So therefore that is again for all עבודה זרה, avoda zara, even
if it's not the way that that עבודה זרה avoda zara is
worshipped. וסמיך ליה, v'samich lei, now how do you know that that's
an act of worship that is so weighty that it's the עבודה
זרה avoda zara that you're חייב מיתה? chayav misa? Because the end
of the פסוק pasuk is והוצאת את האיש ההוא או את האישה
ההיא אל שעריך, v'hotzeisa es ha'ish hahu o es ha'ishah hahi el
she'arecha, that you take out the people who do this worshiping foreign
gods and you execute them. Okay, so we know it's execution because
here the פסוק pasuk speaks about executing and the פסוק pasuk earlier
by זביחה zevicha said יחרם, yecharam, put under the ban, which is
interpreted to mean, you know, which is to execute, okay? So we
know that these things that are like זביחה, zevicha, classic עבודות avodos
in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and השתחוואה hishtachavah are all included
in the prohibition of עבודה זרה avoda zara to be getting the
death penalty. Okay, that's the basic way we learn it out. Now
we're going to spend the next עמוד amud dealing with a counterfactual,
okay, dealing with why not use השתחוואה hishtachavah as the paradigm? We've
used זביחה zevicha as the paradigm, we have a small set plus
prostration. Why not use השתחוואה hishtachavah as the paradigm and have a
much larger set? Okay, so that's going to be the question. So
let's take a look.
Now עונש שמענו אזהרה מניין? onesh shamanu azhara minayin? Oh, we just
did that. No, did we do that? Oh, עונש שמענו. onesh shamanu.
So now we've heard that this is the punishment that they get,
הוצאת את האיש ההוא. hotzeisa es ha'ish hahu. Where is the prohibition
to do השתחוואה? hishtachavah? The prohibition to do classic עבודה avoda we
know. It's interesting that השתחוואה hishtachavah is identified in like a somewhat
different category; it's not classic עבודה, avoda, but it's, you know, it's
classic עבודה avoda outside of a temple context. Anyway, where do we
know that's prohibited? תלמוד לומר: talmud lomar: כי לא תשתחוה לאל אחר.
ki lo sishtachaveh l'el acher. Okay, good. So we have השתחוואה hishtachavah
is added to the list and added to the list of getting
מיתה, misa, plus anything that's like זביחה, zevicha, that's more the classic
category.
Now יכול שאני מרבה המגפף והמנשק והמנעיל? yachol she'ani marbeh hamigafef v'haminashek
v'hamane'il? Maybe other forms of adoration like hugging, kissing, putting on shoes
of the idol? תלמוד לומר: talmud lomar: זובח. zove'ach. No, slaughter. זביחה
zevicha בכלל היתה. b'chlal haysa. זביחה zevicha was included in all of
the forms of worship. ולמה יצאת? v'lamah yatzas?
Why was it singled out? להקיש לה, l'hakish lah, that you should
make associations with it. ולומר לך, v'lomar lach, to tell you מה
זביחה מיוחדת שהיא עבודת פנים וחייבין עליה מיתה. mah zevicha miyuchedes shehi
avodas pnim v'chayavin aleha misa. זביחה, zevicha, what are the distinguishing characteristics
of זביחה? zevicha? It's an act of worship inside the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. It's interesting though, because שחיטה shchita actually—well שחיטה shchita can
be done by a זר, zar, it doesn't need a כהן, kohen,
but the animal actually has to be in the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. It's actually possible to stand outside of עזרת ישראל Ezras Yisrael
and stick your arm in and do the שחיטה. shchita. Yeah, exactly.
But anyway, but nevertheless, the animal—it's a classic form of worship inside
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash וחייבין עליה מיתה v'chayavin aleha misa and
that's included in the death penalty. אף כל שהוא עבודת פנים וחייבין
עליו מיתה. af kol shehu avodas pnim v'chayavin alav misa. So it
has to be like זביחה, zevicha, an עבודת פנים, avodas pnim, plus
bowing down, that's a separate thing. Okay, so that's how I know
that other forms of worship are a negative prohibition, לא תעבדם, lo
sa'avdem, but you don't get מיתה misa for them. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says וחייבין עליו מיתה. v'chayavin alav misa. יצאת השתחוואה לידון
בעצמה. yatzas hishtachavah liddon b'atzmah.
So and prostration is separate; it's not the paradigm. It's the classic
forms of worship in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash plus prostration.
יצאת זביחה לידון על הכלל. yatzas zevicha liddon al haklal. And זביחה
zevicha is the paradigm, זביחה zevicha is
the basic set. Okay,
so
now it asks the reasonable question: לידון
על הכלל כולה אמר מר. liddon al haklal kullah amar mar. So
now אמר מר amar mar means we've quoted an entire text and
now we're going to go back and look at it like piece
by piece. Okay, so אמר מר: amar mar:
מהיכא הוה אמינא? meheicha hava amina?
If it hadn't had the word לאלוהים, L'elohim, I would have thought
that the פסוק pasuk is about just slaughtering outside the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. So the גמרא Gemara says זובח קדשים בחוץ? Zoveach Kodashim
bachutz? How could I have thought that? כרת! kares! We know from
the פסוקים psukim that are explicit about sacrifices out of the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash that that's punishable by כרת, kares, but it's not
the death penalty. So how could I have thought that's what the
פסוק pasuk meant? No. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka deitach amina, I would
have thought to say כי עשו בה התראה, ki asu bei hatala,
if you give warning, then it's the death penalty. כי לא עשו
בה Ki lo asu bei without warning and without witnesses, כרת, kares,
it's כרת. kares. קמשמע לן. Kamashmalan. Okay, this teaches us we're not
talking about קדשים kodshim outside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Excuse me.
We're talking about what do you call—we're talking about worship of עבודה
זרה. avoda zara. Fine. אמר ליה רבה בר רב חנן לאביי: Amar
lei Rava bar Rav Chanan l'Abbaye: Rava bar Rav Chanan says to
Abbaye, why do we make this—like I said, the next עמוד amud
is going to be a
counterfactual—why do we make השתחויה hishtachava the exception and זביחה zvicha the
class? Why don't we make השתחויה hishtachava the class? And we're going
to now see what would—whether that would be a possibility. Okay. אימא
יצא השתחויה ללמד על הכלל, Eima yatza hishtachava lilamed al haklal, let's
say prostration defines the class, the set, כולו. kulo. Now, that's true,
why do you need a פסוק pasuk about זביחה, zvicha, about slaughtering?
השתחויה Hishtachava is very generic, right? It's not limited to inside the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. And if you make השתחויה hishtachava the paradigm,
then the class would include any form of, like, adoration. Okay, hugging,
kissing—all those things we excluded, that would be included if השתחויה hishtachava
was the paradigm. Now, that's true, why do you need a פסוק
pasuk about slaughtering, which is a much narrower concept? Okay. So now
we're going to see what you would have done if השתחויה hishtachava
was the set, what you would have done with the פסוק pasuk
about slaughtering. וכי תימא זובח למה לי, V'chi teima zoveach lamma li,
why do I need the פסוק pasuk about slaughtering? לגופיה, Legufei, לגופיה.
legufei. I need it to tell me something about the act of
slaughtering an animal to עבודה זרה avoda zara itself. What is it
teaching me about that act?
דמחשבים מעבודה לעבודה. Demachshavim mei'avoda l'avoda. What happens if you slaughter an
animal to עבודה זרה, avoda zara, but you're actually thinking, I don't
want this act of slaughter to be the act of worship, I'm
going to take the blood that I get from it and I'll
use the blood to throw on an altar and that'll be my
act of worship? So you got it? You slaughter an animal for
the purpose of using the blood for עבודה זרה. avoda zara. It
sounds like a classic case of קדשים, kodshim, right? If you slaughter
the animal to throw the blood at a wrong time, it makes
the animal פיגול, pigul, if anybody remembers that from קדשים. kodshim. Okay.
So if you, you know, so if you slaughter it not to
be an act of worship but to use the blood in an
act of worship, does it make the animal seen as a sacrifice
to עבודה זרה avoda zara and forbidden in benefit? That's the question.
Okay. Everybody got the scenario? Okay.
Confused? Me neither. If you have זביחה zvicha and then you have
השתחויה, hishtachava, and let's say just those two, why can just, you
know—but once השתחויה hishtachava
is the class, why do you need a narrow, a narrow פסוק
pasuk about זביחה? zvicha?
No, but I'm saying it includes these other four things, whatever it
was. But if you just have one פסוק pasuk on one thing,
one פסוק pasuk on another, then you just say, what, we can't—there's
no rule, it's just like—what, just those two?
No, that's דבר שהיה בכלל ויצא מן הכלל ללמד. davar shehayah baklal
v'yatza min haklal lilamed. That's exactly the phrase that he used before.
Okay, anyway, let's move on. Okay. דמחשבים מעבודה לעבודה. Demachshavim mei'avoda l'avoda.
וכי תימא זובח למה לי? V'chi teima zoveach lamma li? לגופיה. Legufei.
דמחשבים מעבודה לעבודה. Demachshavim mei'avoda l'avoda. דאיתמר, De'itmar, it was said, מחשבים
מעבודה לעבודה machshavim mei'avoda l'avoda is a classic קדשים kodshim phrase, but
we're using it here by עבודה זרה. avoda zara. השוחט בהמה לזרוק
דמה לעבודת
כוכבים, Hashochait beheima lizrok dama l'avodas kochavim, slaughter for the purpose not
that this is the worship itself, to use the blood in עבודה
זרה avoda zara for the act of worship, ולהקטיר חלבה לעבודת כוכבים,
u'l'haktir chelba l'avodas kochavim, or to offer up the fats. רבי יוחנן
אמר אסורה, Rabbi Yochanan amar assura, the בהמה beheima is forbidden. It's
like a—the animal was offered to עבודה זרה, avoda zara, and an
animal offered to עבודה זרה avoda zara is forbidden in benefit. ריש
לקיש אמר מותרת, Reish Lakish amar mutteres, Reish Lakish says it's permissible.
It's not like it was offered to עבודה זרה. avoda zara. You
haven't done an act of worship on the—with the animal itself. By
the way, there's a very cute תוספות. tosafot. תוספות Tosafot says, if
you look at תוספות, tosafot, ריש לקיש אמר מותרת, Reish Lakish amar
mutteres, it says פירוש בהנאה, peireish behana'a, you can get benefit because
it's not an offering to an עבודה זרה avoda zara yet. ולא
באכילה, V'lo b'achila, but you can't eat it. Why not? דמומר לעבודת
כוכבים אסור לאכול משחיטתו. D'mumar l'avodas kochavim assur leechol mishchitah. So the
guy who slaughtered it in the act of doing this act, he
was worshipping עבודה זרה, avoda zara, and therefore the שחיטה shechitah is
invalid. So, so you can't eat because it's not a kosher שחיטה,
shechitah, but it's not an offering to עבודה זרה. avoda zara. And
then he says, אינמי אפילו באכילה שרי, Inami afilu b'achila shari, maybe
you could eat it. כיון דלא היה מומר מעיקרא, Keivan d'lo haya
mumar mei'ikara, since the guy wasn't an idolater before he started doing
the act, he only became an idolater in the process of doing
the act, the שחיטה shechitah would still be valid. בשחיטה זו נעשה
מומר. B'shchitah zu na'aseh mumar. So I thought that was a very
cute little question about at what stage does he become and, you
know, does it change his status and does it invalidate his שחיטה?
shechitah? Anyway, back to this. So there's a debate of Rabbi Yochanan
and Reish Lakish whether the animal's an offering to עבודה זרה. avoda
zara. Now, maybe that's what the word זובח zoveach is teaching. But
where does Rabbi Yochanan get the idea that the animal is an
offering to עבודה זרה? avoda zara? From קדשים. kodshim. That's a normal
principle that by קדשים. kodshim. So according to Rabbi Yochanan, you don't
need any פסוק pasuk about זובח. zoveach. Okay. But Reish Lakish, he
doesn't learn from קדשים. kodshim. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara
does with this. הא ניחא לרבי יוחנן, Ha nicha l'Rabbi Yochanan, for
Rabbi Yochanan I understand, you don't need the word זובח zoveach because
you know everything you need to know from a parallel to קדשים.
kodshim. But Reish Lakish... זובח zoveach is extra, there's nothing to do
with זובח, zoveach, so that's why you can't make the basic principle
is like this: if זובח zoveach is going to wind up being
extra, then the idea to make השתחוה hishtachavah the set and use
זובח zoveach for something else won't work. So if זובח zoveach is
extra, that allows us to go back and say זובח zoveach is
the set and השתחוה hishtachavah is the exception, is the special case.
Okay? So that's what we're trying to get to in order to
explain why we did what we did, to show how זובח zoveach
is going to remain an extra word if we try to do
the other way. So for רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, זובח zoveach would
be an extra word because he learns out this idea of מעבודה
לעבודה me'avodah l'avodah from קדשים. Kodshim. אלא לריש לקיש, Ella l'Reish Lakish,
בעיא קרא, ba'ei kra, but for ריש לקיש Reish Lakish you need
the פסוק pasuk of זובח. zoveach. Now why do you need the
פסוק? pasuk? What are you learning from זובח? zoveach? Okay, what does
זובח zoveach teaching you? You know ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says that
the animal is מותר. mutar. So basically what you're learning from ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish is, hold on let me just go check רש״י
Rashi for just one second. Right, so what you're learning from ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish is they're debating the status of the animal. But
the question is, what's the status of the guy who did it?
Did he do an act of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and is
he חייב מיתה? chayav misah? So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says yes,
once I learn from קדשים Kodshim this is an act of עבודה,
avodah, I'll learn that the guy is חייב מיתה chayav misah as
well. The guy did an act of עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. But
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says I don't learn from קדשים, Kodshim, and
therefore the animal is not forbidden. Well if the animal isn't forbidden,
maybe the guy didn't do an act of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah
and maybe the guy gets off. So that's why you need the
word זובח zoveach to tell me that no, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
would agree that in that case the guy would still have done
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and you would learn it from the word
זובח. zoveach. So for ריש לקיש Reish Lakish we have something to
do with the word זובח. zoveach. So the גמרא Gemara say wait,
מתקיף לה רב פפא. maskif lah Rav Papa. So רב פפא Rav
Papa challenged this. ולרבי יוחנן מי לא בעי קרא? u'l'Rabbi Yochanan mi
lo ba'ei kra? One minute, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan should have to
use the word זובח zoveach as well. עד כאן לא קא אסר
רבי יוחנן אלא בהמה. ad kan lo ka assar Rabbi Yochanan ella
behemah. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is only able to learn from קדשים
Kodshim that the animal has a status of a sacrifice and the
animal is forbidden. אבל גברא, aval gavra, but when it comes to
the question of is the person, did he do a classic act
of עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, גברא בר קטלא הוא? gavra bar katla
hu? There's no basis to say that he's deserving of the death
penalty. ואתא קרא לחיובא דגברא לקטלא. v'ata kra l'chiyuva d'gavra l'katla. So
we're back to our question. Let השתחוה hishtachavah reflect the class, and
let what do you call it, and let זובח zoveach teach you
this special case that it's considered an act of עבודה זרה. Avodah
Zarah. All right, so that's still our question. מתקיף לה רב אחא
בריה דרב איקא. maskif lah Rav Acha brei d'Rav Ika. So רב
אחא בריה דרב איקא Rav Acha brei d'Rav Ika pushed back in
the opposite direction. ולריש לקיש מי בעי קרא? u'l'Reish Lakish mi ba'ei
kra? No, I'll say the exact opposite, that everybody, it's a whole
debate about the status of the animal, but for
everybody it's obvious that the person is liable death penalty. Why? מי
בעי קרא? mi ba'ei kra? עד כאן לא קא שרי ריש לקיש
אלא בהמה. ad kan lo ka shari Reish Lakish ella behemah. Until
now ריש לקיש Reish Lakish was only permitting the animal. That was
the debate, is the animal an offering? In terms of because the
animal itself wasn't yet offered up. אבל גברא בר קטלא הוא. aval
gavra bar katla hu. But the person, of course he's deserving the
death penalty. He did something in the process of worshipping an עבודה
זרה. Avodah Zarah. Okay, it's so funny, he hasn't done the worship
yet, he's only done like a preparatory thing, but the גמרא Gemara
is saying I might have said you don't need זובח zoveach to
teach you that, I could have figured it out by that everybody
would say the person is deserving the death penalty. מידי דהוה אמשתחוה
להר. midi d'hava a'mishtachaveh l'har. Now you'll say oh how could it
be, if the animal could be permissible, how could the person have
done an act of עבודה זרה? Avodah Zarah? We have things like
this. Consider a person who bowed down to a mountain. דהר מותר,
d'har mutar, the mountain is permissible. You don't go start making parts
of the world forbidden, that's learned from a פסוק. pasuk. ועובדה בסייף,
v'ovdah b'sayif, ועובדה בסייף. v'ovdah b'sayif. And the guy who worshipped it
gets
executed by the sword. Now the reason it says the sword is
because it's talking about, why say sword? It should have said סקילה.
sekilah. But it's talking about a non-Jew. Okay? Because it's learned from
a פסוק אלהיהם על ההרים ולא ההרים אלהיהם. pasuk eloheihem al he'harim
v'lo he'harim eloheihem. Their gods are on the mountains but the mountains
don't become their gods. So the גמרא Gemara is saying I could
have lived with a scenario where the animal is not forbidden and
the act is still an act of עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. And
maybe I don't need a פסוק pasuk to tell me that. Maybe
I could have figured that out by myself. Okay so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר ליה רב אחא מדפתי לרבינא. amar
lei Rav Acha mi'Difti l'Ravina. So רב אחא מדפתי Rav Acha mi'Difti
said to רבינא, Ravina, למאי דקאמר ליה, l'mai d'ka'amar lei, so now
we're good. We got the word זובח zoveach being extra, and that
proves that זובח zoveach has to represent the class and השתחוה hishtachavah
is a special case. Okay? So למאי דקאמר ליה רבה בר בר
חנה לאביי, l'mai d'ka'amar lei Rabbah bar bar Chanah l'Abaye, אימא ייתי
השתחוה ותלמד על הכלל כולו. eima yeisi hishtachavah v'silmad al ha'klal kulo.
One minute, going back to this counter-factual suggestion that we had, that
the class would be השתחוה hishtachavah and prostration and therefore every form
of sort of respect for. worship is what the גמרא's gemara going
to say, you know, worship of adoration, of respect, every form would
have been included in the death penalty. According to that approach, האי
עבודה לימותי מאי? hai avodah limutei mai? The פסוק pasuk says that
you'll say how do these non-Jews worship their gods? איכה יעבדו הגוים
האלה את אלהיהם. eicha ya'avdu hagoyim ha'eileh et eloheihem. So because it
says how do they worship, how do they worship, meaning it refers
to their unique form of worship, the worship that is specific to
that god. Okay, so we've got, right, what we normally have is,
we have זביחה zevicha defining the class, okay, and the class there
includes, that's a class of עבודת פנים, avodat pnim, okay, and that's
a class that includes, you know, מקטיר maktir and מנסך, menseich, okay.
And then we have also a case by itself of השתחוה, hishtachavah,
השתחוה, hishtachavah, השתחוה. hishtachavah. Okay, that, I think I spelled that right.
Anyway, that is, I think it's spelled with an אלף. aleph. Anyway,
that is, those are for all עבודה זרות. avoda zaras. And then
we have the case of עבודה כדרכה. avoda k'darkah. Okay, whatever is
classic for that particular עבודה זרה. avoda zara. Where do we learn
whatever is classic for that particular עבודה זרה avoda zara from the
פסוק pasuk of איכה יעבדו הגוים האלה את אלהיהם? eicha ya'avdu hagoyim
ha'eileh et eloheihem? Okay. How do they worship means their specific form
of worship. Okay, so we have these which are the classic, and
then the next, and then the specific one based on that פסוק.
pasuk. Fine, that's great if this defines the class. But if השתחוה
hishtachavah defines the class, then this class of השתחוה hishtachavah is going
to basically already be every form of worship, right? So why do
you need this פסוק? pasuk? Okay, so it says according to that,
איכה יעבדו לימותי מאי, eicha ya'avdu limutei mai, what does it exclude
since השתחוה hishtachavah already basically includes everything? Okay, so the גמרא gemara
says, וכי תימא לימותי הפעור עצמו לזובחים, v'chi teima limutei haporeh atzmo
l'zovchim, maybe it's to exclude forms of worship that are not honorable.
For example, if you have defecating. Now that's a form of worship
that's done for בעל פעור, Ba'al Peor, but let's say instead you
did an act of defecating to a normal idol that a normal,
you know, foreign god that normally you would bring sacrifices to. So
that would not be a natural thing to do, right? So maybe
that would be excluded based on this פסוק pasuk of איכה יעבדו,
eicha ya'avdu, that that's unacceptable. It has to be a, you know,
an honorable form of worship. So the גמרא gemara says, מהשתחוה נפקא.
mihishtachavah na'fka. I know that from the class of prostrating. מאי השתחוה
דרך כבוד? mai hishtachavah derech kavod? השתחוה hishtachavah doesn't include everything, השתחוה
hishtachavah includes acts of worship that are showing honor. אף כל דרך
כבוד, af kol derech kavod, anything that shows honor. Okay? So if
that's true, השתחוה hishtachavah includes everything, why do I still need this
פסוק? pasuk? What is this פסוק pasuk that says only classic ways,
what does it exclude? Now, of course, what you could have said
is that it's not excluding, it's including. It includes the case like
the one who defecates to בעל פעור. Ba'al Peor. That's not similar
to השתחוה, hishtachavah, right? That's not because it's not an honorable act,
but it is a classic form of worship. But the גמרא gemara
isn't saying that for some reason, תוספות Tosafot discusses that, and it
wants to know if השתחוה hishtachavah includes everything, what does this exclude?
Okay, so the גמרא gemara says, אלא לימותי הפעור עצמו למרקוליס. ella
limutei haporeh atzmo l'Markolis. If somebody defecates to מרקוליס. Markolis. מרקוליס Markolis
is a thing you would throw rocks at. סלקא דעתך אמינא, salika
daitach amina, I might say, הואיל ועבודה בזיון היא, ho'il va'avoda bizayon
hi, since מרקוליס Markolis you also do an act of worship which
is a degrading type of an act, you know, I'm so therefore,
אף כל בזיון, af kol bizayon, so maybe any type of act,
even an act that's showing that's a form of like degrading, maybe
that also would be included and you'd be חייב. chayav. קא משמע
לן kamashma lan no. Okay, so fine, that's what I would have
done. I would have said השתחוה hishtachavah is all acts of כבוד
kavod and this says basically says things that are distinctive even if
they're not כבוד, kavod, like הפעור לפעור, haporeh l'Peor, defecating to פעור,
Peor, but not things that are not acts of כבוד kavod even
to gods that are worshipped through other forms of disgraceful types of
acts. That's what I would have done if השתחוה hishtachavah would have
been the class. But השתחוה hishtachavah is not the class. This is
the class plus השתחוה hishtachavah special case plus classic forms of worship
if they're specific to that god. Okay, so now we say like
this. אלא הדר אמר רבי אליעזר, ella hadar amar Rabbi Eliezer, now
what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said, מנין לזובח בהמה למרקוליס שהוא חייב?
minayin l'zoveach beheima l'Markolis shehu chayav? How do I know if somebody
brings an animal to מרקוליס Markolis that he's חייב? chayav? Right, which
is basically our question, a classic form of worship to a god
that's not normally worshipped at, שנאמר, shene'emar, ולא יזבחו. v'lo yizbechu. Don't
bring their anymore their sacrifices to the, you know, to the whatever
goat gods or whatever the שעירים se'irim are. אם אינו עניין לכדרכה,
im eino inyan lekdarkah, if that's not needed to prohibit what is
a natural form of worship, דכתיב איך יעבדו הגויים האלה, de'chtiv eich
ya'avdu ha'goyim ha'eleh, use it to teach me even when it's not
a natural form. Okay, so so basically and the way we have
it is we've got these things, but how do we know to
apply these things even when it's not natural for that עבודה זרה,
avoda zara, not normally done? How do we know that you know
even when it's not natural? So the פסוק pasuk that links it,
meaning we know you're חייב מיתה, chayav misa, that we learn from
זובח לאלהים יחרם. zoveach le'elohim yacharom. But where is the פסוק pasuk
that prohibits it? So the פסוק pasuk that prohibits it is ולא
יזבחו עוד את זבחיהם. velo yizbechu od et zivcheihem. That פסוק, pasuk,
right, ולא יזבחו עוד את זבחיהם, velo yizbechu od et zivcheihem, so
so we have זובח לאלהים zoveach le'elohim ach what am I becoming
like what do you call it dyslexic זובח zoveach oops לאלהים יחרם,
le'elohim yacharom, okay, that's telling you you get מיתה misa and ולא
יזבחו את זבחיהם velo yizbechu et zivcheihem is telling you it's prohibited.
Even if it's not the normal things that's done. That's when this
is for כלל. klal. So I need this to tell me you
get מיתה misa and this to tell me that that there's the
prohibition even if it's not normal. But again if השתחויה hishtachavaya is
the כלל klal and then we're already including all things that are
that are acts of honor, why do I need this specific פסוק
pasuk to tell me that זביחה zvicha is prohibited? Alright, it's not
exactly clear why I can't have it say the same thing but
anyway we'll work on it. So it says, so אם אינו תניהו
עניין לשלא כדרכה. im eino tenaihu inyan leshe'lo kdarkah. שלא כדרכה מהשתחויה
נפקא she'lo kdarkah mishtachavaya nafka but if השתחויה hishtachavaya was the כלל,
klal, I would have learned that already from the idea of השתחויה.
hishtachavaya. No, so the גמרא Gemara says התם בזובח להכעיס. hatam bizoveach
le'hach'is. I might have thought that what if somebody and with we're
going to see like the flip side of this is so great.
Like you know we talk in הלכה halacha about somebody that does
an עבירה להכעיס, aveira le'hach'is, right, does an עבירה aveira to to
anger God. So here the גמרא Gemara imagines somebody who is bringing
an act of a קרבן korban to a certain idol not as
a form of worship of the idol because remember we're talking about
a case that it's not the natural way the idol is worshipped.
He's doing it to spite the idol. You Zeus, you don't like
it when I slaughter, you only want certain sacrifices, you don't want
you only want X as your form of worship, you don't want
slaughtering animals as your form of worship. Well I'm fed up with
you so I'm going to slaughter an animal to you as a
form of worship. Okay, so it's not done as a way of
showing fealty, it's done as a way of expressing spite. And nevertheless
that is prohibited from this פסוק. pasuk. Although רש"י Rashi says since
it's a way of showing sort of spite and not fealty, רש"י
Rashi says it's not חייב מיתה. chayav misa. רש"י Rashi also says
that the person who is doing it להכעיס le'hach'is doesn't accept that
god as a god. But that's not necessarily true. You know, once
if you don't accept that god as a god then why do
you have to bother doing it להכעיס? le'hach'is? להכעיס le'hach'is means you're
in a relationship. Okay, so anyway it's interesting that רש"י Rashi says
that's with it's without believing in that god. Anyway that's what I
would have done if השתחויה hishtachavaya was the כלל. klal. But השתחויה
hishtachavaya is not the כלל. klal. So from these two I know
forms of worship, these forms of worship you get מיתה misa and
it's prohibited even if it's not the natural thing to do. Same
is true about השתחויה hishtachavaya and the natural forms are included over
there. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. רב המנונא,
Rav Hamnuna, רב Rav now רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna אירכסו irkasu oh
my god רב המנונא אירכסו ליה תרי תורי. Rav Hamnuna irkasu lei
trei tore. רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna lost some what do you see
some oxen, thank you. פגע ביה רבה. paga bei Rabba. רבה Rabba
bumped into him. I don't know why we need to know he
was lost some oxen but anyway he was wandering around and רבה
Rabba bumped into him. אמר ליה מתניתן אדדי. amar lei matnitan adadi.
So רב חסדא Rav Chisda was רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna was saying
"Do you know where my oxen are?" and רבה Rabba was saying
"Wait wait wait I have some I have a question to you
about about עבודה זרה." avoda zara. Okay it's so funny it's like
can we talk about this some other time after I find my
oxen? But no, okay. רבה Rabba said "Wait wait I I want
you to answer this problem I've got." תנן, tenan, our משנה Mishna
says העובד עבודת כוכבים, ha'oved avodat kochavim, if somebody worships עבודה זרה
avoda zara חייב. chayav. עובד אין oved in only when the person
does an act of worship. אומר לא omer lo if he just
says "I'm planning on worshipping" then you're not חייב. chayav. והנן תנן
vehanan tenan but we're going to teach in a משנה Mishna coming
up האומר ha'omer somebody says אעבוד evod "I will worship" or אלך
ואעבוד elech ve'evod "Let's I will go and worship" meaning I have
to travel. נלך ונעבוד nelech vena'avod "Let's all go and worship" at
that already you're חייב chayav even planning to do it. Now I
gotta pause for a moment because it's a bizarre question that רבה
Rabba is asking. The משנה Mishna over there is talking about not
when somebody is חייב chayav for עבודה זרה, avoda zara, it's talking
about when somebody is חייב chayav for being a מסית. mesit. A
מסית mesit is a seducer to עבודה זרה. avoda zara. So the
the simple reading of that משנה Mishna is... says, "Hey, let's go
worship עבודה זרה." avodah zarah. Now, is that person already a מסית?
meiseit? No, cause he has to be successful. So what does it
mean to be successful? Does it mean that you have to actually
worship עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? So the משנה mishna says as soon
as you say yes, let's go, I'm going to go with you.
Then then the person was already a מסית meiseit and is חייב.
chayav. So it's talking about the מסית meiseit being חייב chayav when
the other guy agrees even before the other guy has actually done
it. What our גמרא Gemara is assuming, what רבא Rava is assuming,
is that the מסית meiseit that it's not that maybe the מסית
meiseit wouldn't be חייב chayav unless the guy would be חייב. chayav.
So it's what רבא Rava says as soon as the guy says
yes, I'm going to go worship, the guy is also חייב chayav
in עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. The one who agreed to worship has
now חייב chayav for doing an act of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
That's quite bizarre. He just said he was going to do it,
right? By the way, I should say and I don't know if
this is in the background there, but this fits in to a
general principle that the גמרא Gemara has where the גמרא Gemara says
מחשבה טובה הקדוש ברוך הוא מצרפה למעשה. machshava tova hakadosh baruch hu
metzarfa lemaaseh. If you have a good thought, you're planning on doing
some מצוה mitzvah and something happened and you weren't able to do
it, God gives you credit for doing it. Okay, but מחשבה רעה
אין הקדוש ברוך הוא מצרפה למעשה. machshava raah ein hakadosh baruch hu
metzarfa lemaaseh. If you're planning on doing an עבירה aveira God doesn't
give you consider it like you've done it. Except for עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah. Okay, so here you have somebody planning on doing עבודה
זרה avodah zarah but saying it's חייב מיתה chayav misa the way
רבא Rava is reading this. So how is that possible? What about
our משנה mishna that says you have to actually do it? Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says אמר ליה באומר איני מקבלה עלי אלא
בעבודה. amar leih be'omer eini mekabla alai ela ba'avodah. He says ah,
so the answer seems to be a strange one. The answer is
let me go find my ox. No, the answer is the answer
is he's saying that you're right. Normally if a guy said yes,
let's go be עובד עבודה זרה, oved avodah zarah, he would be
חייב chayav from that minute. But if the guy said I don't
I'm not going to accept the עבודה זרה avodah zarah as my
god until I do the act of worship, then you're not חייב
chayav until you do the act of worship. Very bizarre, like you
know, why would saying yes, let's go, be considered an act of
worship? So תוספות Tosafot says it actually isn't an act of worship
per se, it fits into the category of the משנה mishna as
מקבלה עלי באלוה. mekabla alai be'elo'ah. Remember the משנה mishna said that
even accepting this foreign god as your god is considered an עבודה.
avodah. So תוספות Tosafot says if the guy says yes, I'm going
to go worship the עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, you're חייב chayav not
for sacrificing or doing whatever, you're חייב chayav for accepting that as
your god. Okay, but if you say so if you say but
if you say yes let's go worship but I'm not going to
accept it as my god until we get there, then you're not
חייב chayav until you do the עבודה. avodah. Okay, so that's the
way תוספות Tosafot reads it that when are you חייב chayav when
you say you're going to do it if that becomes an act
of accepting that as your god. Okay, so now that's answer number
one. רב יוסף אמר תנאי שקלת מאי עלמא, Rav Yosef amar tana'ei
shaklat mei'alma, what, you're just quoting random תנאים? Tannaim? You quote one
משנה mishna and another משנה. mishna. תנאי, tana'ei, it's a debate between
the משניות mishnayos whether you're חייב chayav from the moment you accept
it. תנאי דתניא דתניא ברייתא, tana'ei detanya detanya beraisa, האומר בואו ועבדוני,
ha'omer bo'u ve'avduni, if somebody says, somebody makes himself a god and
says come worship me, is that person a מסית? meiseit? Is a
מסית meiseit only when they're seducing you to worship another god? What
if they're trying to get you to worship themselves? Is that a
מסית? meiseit? בואו ועבדוני. bo'u ve'avduni. So רבי מאיר מחייב, Rabbi Meir
mechayeiv, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is מחייב mechayeiv the person for being
a מסית, meiseit, ורבי יהודה פוטר, v'Rabbi Yehuda poter, רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda exempts. Now again the focus seems to be on the seducer,
but we're also flipping it to the one being seduced, or incited
might be a better word than seduced. But anyway, is he also
if he says yes, I'll worship you, at that moment is he
חייב chayav for עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this, היכא דפלחו, heicha depalchu, if the person actually
worshipped this person, if שמעון Shimon actually worshipped ראובן, Reuven, brought a
sacrifice, כולי עלמא לא פליגי, kuli alma lo peligi, everybody would agree
that that's עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. How do you know that's considered
an עבודה זרה avodah zarah bringing turning a person into an עבודה
זרה? avodah zarah? דכתיב לא תעשה לך פסל. dechitiv lo ta'aseh lecha
pesel. Now this is of course this is a very cute read
of the פסוק. pasuk. לא תעשה לך פסל, lo ta'aseh lecha pesel,
don't make yourself into an idol. Don't make yourself into like you
know a an object of worship. So if they if you worship
a person as a god, yes, that's עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, everybody
would agree to that, and presumably the person would be חייב chayav
for being a מסית. meiseit. כי פליגי, ki peligi, when did they
debate? בדיבור בעלמא, bedibbur be'alma, that the people just said yes, we
will worship you as a god. רבי מאיר סבר דיבורא מילתא היא,
Rabbi Meir savar dibbura milta hi, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that
already is considered an act of acceptance as a god, I'll read
it through תוספות's Tosafot lens, it's an act of accepting as a
god and therefore you're חייב, chayav, ורבי יהודה סבר דיבורא לאו מילתא
היא, v'Rabbi Yehuda savar dibbura lav milta hi, it's not an act
of accepting as a god. So here this question is saying I
will go and worship considered accepting that as a god, he says
that is a debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. So our משנה mishna that says you have to actually
worship holds that it is not an act of an act of
accepting as a god. The later משנה mishna that says when you
say you'll go holds the position that it is an act of
accepting that as a god. Okay, so there's no contradiction in the
משניות, mishnayos, it's two different opinions. גמרא Gemara says, הדר אמר רב
יוסף, hadar amar Rav Yosef, then רב יוסף Rav Yosef says, לאו
מילתא היא דאמרי. lav milta hi de'amri. You know what? That resolution
I said that it's a debate of תנאים, Tanayim, that's not true.
דאפילו רבי יהודה בדיבורא נמי מיחייב. da'afilu Rabbi Yehuda bedibbura nami mechayev.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda under normal cases says if a person says
I will go and worship, he is חייב. chayav. דתניא, detanya, we
taught in a ברייתא, braisa, רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, עובד
אינו חייב, oved eino chayav, the person is not חייב. chayav. Now
again, does it mean the מסית mesis isn't חייב chayav or the
person who agrees isn't חייב? chayav? We're reading this from the perspective
of the person who agreed. The person who agrees is not חייב
chayav for עבודה זרה Avoda Zara עד שיאמר ad sheyomar unless he
says אעבוד, e'evod, I will worship, אילך ואעבוד, elech ve'e'evod, I'll go
and worship, נילך ונעבוד, nelech vene'evod, let's go and worship. Okay, so
you see that everybody agrees that verbal agreement to go and worship
makes you חייב. chayav. So if that's true, what is the debate
about the person who makes himself a god? That's a unique debate
about that case. Okay, so במאי קמיפלגי, bemai kamiflagi, so what is
their debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir?
במסית לעצמו, bemesis la'atzmo, somebody who's inciting people to worship himself. Okay,
ואמרי לה, ve'amrei lah, במסית לעצמו, bemesis la'atzmo, ואמרי אין, ve'amrei in,
and the people that he's inciting say, "Yes, we're going to go
worship you." Okay, קמיפלגי, kamiflagi, that's the debate. מר סבר, mar savor,
מסית לעצמו שמיעי ליה, mesis la'atzmo shemi'ei leih, that when you incite
someone, the person who incites others to worship himself, people will listen
to him. Okay, ואינהו דקאמרי ליה קושטא הוא, ve'inhu deka'amri leih kushta
hu, when they say yes, they're being serious, and therefore the person
is חייב chayav as a מסית mesis and they're חייב chayav for
accepting him as a god. ומר סבר, umar savor, the other one
holds, מסית לעצמו לא שמיעי ליה. mesis la'atzmo lo shemi'ei leih. No,
when you incite a person, the person who incites people, the people
are not really going to listen to him. That's a crazy thing.
מאי אמרי, mai amri, people will say, מאי שנא איהו מינן, mai
shana ihu minan, he's just a human being, how is he different
than us? What, he's a god? How could that be? Okay, ואי
דקאמרי, ve'i deka'amri, ah, they say yes we will worship you, אחוכי
עליה, achuchei aleih, they're just mocking him. All right, so anyway, so
the debate is do we take people saying that they'll worship this
person as a god serious or not? So it's a unique debate
in when the person puts himself up as a god. But there's
a Christian thing going on there? What? Is there a Christian? I'm
wondering about that, whether there's that whole Christian idea in the background.
Yeah, and the גמרא Gemara sort of tries to make that point,
like isn't this absurd to think that a person could be a
god? Yeah, that's, I was very much wondering that, yeah. Okay, so
but everybody agrees in a normal case of an עבודה זרה, Avoda
Zara, as soon as you say yes I'll go and worship, again
the way we're reading the משנה mishna later on, is that that's
an act of accepting as a god and that's an act of
עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. So how come our משנה mishna says you
have to actually do the worship? All right, so the only answer
we've gotten so far is that in our משנה mishna you haven't
yet, you've made it clear that you're not accepting that god as
a god just yet. And therefore saying you're going to go worship
is not yet the accepting of it as a god. That's the
only answer we have so far. Now we're going to have some
other answers. ומתניתין, umatanitin, now רב יוסף Rav Yosef says, here's my
answer to resolve the משניות. mishnayos. כאן ביחיד הניסתתים כאן ברבים הניסתתים.
kan beyachid hanistatim kan berabbim hanistatim. It depends whether it's an individual
being incited or a mass number of people. יחיד לא מימלך וטעי
בתריה. yachid lo mimlach veta'ei basrei. לא מימלך וטעי בתריה. lo mimlach
veta'ei basrei. So if only an individual is being incited, so, I'm
sorry, I'm going to write the first time. יחיד לא מימלך, yachid
lo mimlach, if you incite an individual and the individual says yes
I'll go and worship, he won't have a change of heart, וטעי
בתריה, veta'ei basrei, and he'll be led astray. So in an individual,
as soon as he says I will go and worship, that is
already an act of עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, an act of accepting.
But ברבים, berabbim, but if it's masses, מימלכי ולא טעו בתריה. mimlachi
velo ta'u basrei. It's funny, you could have said the opposite, that
if it's masses everybody is sort of peer pressuring everybody else. But
here it says if there's a masses that are being incited, some
people might speak up and you know and it could sort of
lead to people you know having remorse or having second thoughts and
ultimately we would hope that if you're trying to incite a mass
number of people that in the end it won't succeed. So when
you're inciting an individual and the individual says yes, boom, we assume
that you've succeeded and that person is also חייב chayav for עבודה
זרה. Avoda Zara. But if you're inciting a masses and they say
yes, we don't yet assume success, you're not yet חייב chayav and
they're not yet חייב chayav for עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. That's his
answer. אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav Yosef, מנא אמינא לה, mina amina
lah, where do I get this idea, the difference between the individual
and the masses? דכתיב, dichsiv, because the verse says, לא תאבה לו
ולא תשמע אליו. lo sovei lo velo tishma eilav. This is by
the מסית, mesis, the inciter, don't like, don't, you know, agree to
him and don't listen to him.
הא אבה ושמע חייב. Ha-avah v'shama chayav.
But as soon as you listen, you are חייב. chayav. Now at
this point, this seems to be a shift. This is where תוספות
Tosafos reads it. It's a shift from saying that the problem when
they say yes is accepting the God as a God to saying
no no no. They didn't- it's not because they've accepted it as
a God. It's unique to the context of being incited. Since the
verse when somebody is inciting you says don't listen to the inciter,
so therefore from that verse we learn that in a context of
being incited, as soon as you say yes, then you've transgressed and
that's considered עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So if nobody was inciting you
and you on your own said, I am going to go and
worship, you wouldn't be חייב. chayav. Okay, but in a context of
being incited and agreeing and hitching your wagon to this God, then
you are חייב. chayav. Alright, so now what we have is according
to רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, if the person does it himself, it's
only when he does actual עבודה. avodah. In a case of being
incited where the פסוק pasuk specifically says לא תאבה לו, lo tove
lo, so in that type of a case when you do it
by yourself it's really about actually doing worship. But in case of
being incited, okay, it's about agreeing and hitching your wagon. In this
case, as soon as you agree and hitch on, you're חייב chayav
even though you haven't done an עבודה. avodah. But there's a difference
between a יחיד yachid and a רבים. rabbim. Okay, an individual we
will say will go through with it, will go through and therefore
is חייב chayav as soon as he says yes. And the masses
we say might not and therefore they are exempt even after they
said yes. But this obligation of being incited, the transgression is not
because of worship, the transgression is here because of agreeing to worship.
Okay, an agreeing to worship that we expect you'll see will actually
be actualized, you're חייב chayav right as soon as you agree in
the context of being incited. But when it's not in that context,
then you actually have to worship, which suggests an easier resolution of
the משנה, Mishnah, not the difference between an individual and the masses,
but the easier resolution of the משנה Mishnah is, are you being
incited or not being incited? And that's what we're about to say.
So let's take a look. So it says like this. איתיבי אביי,
Esvei Abaye, so אביי Abaye challenges: מי שני בין ניסת רבים לניסת
יחיד? Mi shani bein nisas rabbim lenisas yachid? What's your basis of
distinguishing between an individual and the masses? והתניא, Veha tanya, we taught
a ברייתא: Braisa: כי יסיתך אחיך בן אמך, Ki yesitcha achicha ben
imecha, when your brother, your mother's son, incites you. אחד יחיד הניסס
ואחד רבים הניסתין. Echad yachid hanisas ve-echad rabbim hanisatin. It doesn't matter
whether the individual is being incited or the masses. But there is
a difference in the punishment. Here's a difference is. והוציא הכתוב יחיד
מכלל רבים ורבים מכלל יחיד. Vehotsia hakasuv yachid miklal rabbim verabbim miklal
yachid. There are ways in which they're not in the same category.
יחיד מכלל רבים, Yachid miklal rabbim, an individual's not like the masses:
להחמיר על גופו, lehachmir al gufo, the punishment for an individual, ironically,
is more weighty than the punishment for a whole city that worships
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. A whole city is by the sword, right?
That's עיר הנדחת. Ir Hanidachas. An individual is סקילה, sekilah, and we
say that סקילה sekilah is a harsher punishment. So the individual gets
the harsher punishment on his body: ולהקל על ממונו, ulehakel al mamono,
but easier on his money, his money isn't destroyed, right? His property
isn't destroyed. רבים מכלל יחיד Rabbim miklal yachid and the masses are
different than the individual: להקל על גופן, lehakel al gufan, the punishment
on their body is lighter, it's by the sword: ולהחמיר על ממונן,
ulehachmir al mamonan, but what you do to their property is worse,
you destroy it. Anyway, אביי Abaye says: בהא מילתא הוא דשאני. bah
milta hu deshani. That's the one difference between the masses and the
individual. Okay, but אבל בכל מילי כי הדדי נינהו, aval bechol milei
ki hadadi ninhu, for all other things they would be the same.
So אביי Abaye says, I don't buy the difference between agreeing whether
it's an individual being incited or masses, at what stage they're חייב.
chayav. They'd all be חייב chayav at the same stage. As soon
as they said yes, they'd be חייב. chayav. אלא אמר אביי, Ela
amar Abaye, כאן בניסס מפי עצמו כאן בניסס מפי אחרים. kan benisas
mipi atzmo kan benisas mipi acheirim. That is clearly the better difference.
Okay, not an individual and masses. This is about being incited and
saying yes. Okay, doesn't matter individual or masses. So that's the later
משנה. Mishnah. The later משנה Mishnah says as soon as you say,
I will go and worship, because you've hitched your wagon to this
God, you are now חייב chayav as if you've worshipped. Okay, it's
still funny, the משנה Mishnah could have been just talking about when
the guy is חייב, chayav, not when you're חייב. chayav. But we're
saying if you're incited and say yes, I'll go with you, okay,
I will, then you're חייב chayav as soon as you say yes.
If you're deciding on your own, you're only חייב chayav when you
actually do the worship. Okay, so that's clearly a very nice clean
answer. Wait, let me just finish. Okay, כאן בניסס מפי אחרים. מפי
עצמו. kan benisas mipi acheirim. Mipi atzmo. Now of course the reason
he gives a difference is not based on the verse. I would
have liked to have based it on the... verse and it says
there's a different category. There's a category of being incited and there's
a category of worshipping. But אביי Abaye says the difference is whether
you're going to go through with it or not. Okay? מסית מפי
עצמו, meisis mipi atzmo, מפי עצמו ממלך. mipi atzmo mimlach. If you're
deciding on your own, you'll maybe think better of it. מפי אחרים,
mipi acherim, but if somebody else is exerting influence on you and
you're saying yes, גריר בתרייהו, garir basraiyhu, they will continue to exert
that influence and you'll be drawn after them. It's a good מוסר
mussar for like the אלול Elul period, the ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
period, right? If you're making decisions on your own, you know, you're,
you know, you're more able to rethink things and so on. When
you're following a group or you know, when you're letting other people
have influence, you'll wind up doing wrong things. So the way he
makes the difference is whether you're going to go through with it
or not, maybe he's explaining the logic of the difference, but still
I would say that there's a conceptually different category. By doing it
by yourself, the category is עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. You're not חייב
chayav until you do the עבודה. avodah. But if you're incited and
you say yes, the category isn't עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, the category
is like, you know, hooking up with this guy and being and
probably you'll wind up actualizing it, so there as soon as you
say yes, you are already חייב chayav from that moment. Yes, you
had a question, David? What does it say הסית hasis to your
brother, the son of your mother? That's a separate issue. We learned
we use that to learn הלכות ייחוד, halachos yichud, but we're not
going to worry about that right now. Okay, let's get, we're doing
well. Let's get to the two dots. Okay, רבא אמר, Rava amar,
now רבא Rava has a different answer. אידי ואידי במסית מפי אחרים.
idi ve'idi be'meisis mipi acherim. No, even our משנה Mishnah could be
that other people are inciting you. So why in our משנה Mishnah
do you have to actually worship? Why is it not enough to
say yes? So הא דאמר ליה כך אוכלת כך שותה כך מטיבה
כך מריעה. ha de'amar leh kach ocheles kach shosah kach meitivah kach
meriah. In one case, it's how influential the inciter is. If the
inciter sort of starts talking up about their god, "Oh, this is
the way it eats and this is the way it drinks and
we have such cool forms of worship and this is how it's
so good to its followers and this is the way it punishes
people who transgress, you gotta worship this god, it's amazing," right? So
in that type of a case, as soon as you say yes,
we assume you're going to go through with it, okay, because it's,
because you know the, you've been given a heavy sell job. Okay?
And in that case, as soon as you say yes, you're חייב.
chayav. But if he just said, "Hey, let's go worship," and you
said yes, then we assume you'll have second thoughts and you're not
חייב chayav until you actually worship. הא דלא אמר ליה כך אוכלת
כך שותה ha de'lo amar leh kach ocheles kach shosah etc. אמר
רבא מנא אמינא לה, amar Rava mna amina lah, where do I
get this idea that it matters the sell job that you're doing?
דכתיב de'ksiv because the verse says מאלוהי העמים אשר סביבותיכם הקרובים אליך
או הרחוקים ממך. me'elohei ha'amim asher sevivoseichem ha'kerovim eilecha o ha'rechokim mimecha.
He's going to try to incite you to worship these gods from
the gods of the nations that are around you, whether they're the
nations that are nearby or that are far away. So רבא Rava
says מה טיבן של קרובים מה טיבן של רחוקים, mah tivan shel
kerovim mah tivan shel rechokim, why does the verse have to mention
whether they're nearby gods or faraway gods? So הכי קאמר ליה, hachi
ka'amar leh, here is what the פסוק pasuk is trying to tell
you why you shouldn't listen to the guy. Why should you not
listen to the guy? מטיבותן של קרובים, mitivusan shel kerovim, from the
nature, another word טוב, tov, it's like from the nature, from the
character of those that are near you אתה למד מה טיבותן של
רחוקים, atah lamed mah tivusan shel rechokim, you can figure out the
character of those that are far away. Meaning you're surrounded by these
pagan gods, you see that it's a bunch of nonsense. So what
this guy will come to do is he'll try to sell you
on some god you've never heard of. He'll say, "Yeah, these gods
are nonsense, but you gotta see the god we worship over there
in מואב, Moav, that's a real god." Okay? And then you're going
to maybe be persuaded. So the verse is saying, "You know what?
Look around you. The gods over in those other nations are no
different than the gods around you and you can figure out that
it's all nonsense." Okay? But anyway, but because the פסוק pasuk has
to do that to counteract the sell job that this guy will
do and try to convince you to worship these faraway gods, you
see that the context of the verse is that the guy is
doing a sell job on you. Okay? So מאי לאו דאמר ליה,
mai lav de'amar leh, so it must be that the context of
the verse is that he's telling you כך אוכלת כך שותה כך
מטיבה כך מריעה. kach ocheles kach shosah kach meitivah kach meriah. שמע
מינה. shma minah. So therefore רבא Rava says the verse where it
says as soon as you say yes, don't listen to him, implying
that as soon as you say yes you're חייב, chayav, is when
he did a whole heavy sell job on you. And then we'll
assume that the saying yes you've really committed to it. But if
it were just said, "Hey, let's do it," and you said sure,
that's not enough to be חייב. chayav. Then it's like the case
of deciding on your own and you're only חייב chayav when you
do an act of worship. You're not חייב chayav just because you've
sort of said yes because you're not really persuaded yet, you're not
really, you know, totally hooked onto his wagon. Okay, one last answer.
רב אשי אמר בסיפא בישראל מומר. Rav Ashi amar be'seifa be'Yisrael mumar.
רב אשי Rav Ashi says, "No, the difference is that the only
person who's חייב chayav when they say yes is the is a
Jew who's already been עובד עבודה זרה." oved avodah zarah. So that
guy, an apostate, that guy of course his yes means a yes,
his actions have already shown it. Okay? But any other person, even
after a whole big sell job and all of that, saying yes
is not enough, you have to actually do the worship. Okay? And
רבינא אמר, Ravina amar, רבינא Ravina says, לא זו אף זו קתני.
lo zu af zu katani. No, actually, our משניות Mishnayot aren't contradicting
and רבינא's Ravina the most stringent position. He says, our משנה Mishna
says if you worship you're חייב. chayav. The next משנה Mishna tells
you, you know what? You don't even have to worship, just saying
you're going to go worship is חייב. chayav. So according to רבינא
Ravina it seems like anybody, even on your own, even without being
incited and so on. So we have a whole range of different
opinions. The easiest explanation because let's face it, it is very hard
to understand why saying you're going to do it means that you've
done עבודה זרה. avoda zara. So the only way to understand it
is either what תוספות Tosfos said, that it's an act of accepting
that god as a god and that's why you're חייב, chayav, or
because it's specifically in the category of מסית, meisit, it's specifically in
the category of being incited. And when you're in that category and
you say yes, you become part of this whole guy's enterprise to
get people to worship עבודה זרה avoda zara and so on, right?
That's the case when you're חייב chayav by saying yes. But if
you're not, either if it's possible you won't listen to the guy
in the end because he didn't do a good enough sell job
or something like that, or you're not being incited, then it's really
an act of עבודה זרה avoda zara and you really have to
do the worship. Alright. אביי אמר, Abaye amar, אביי Abaye says, I'm
sorry, איתמר. Itmar. Now, now he introduces with—actually we're going to end
here because this now introduces a very important new debate of אביי
Abaye and רבא Rava and we will pick up with this on
שבת. Shabbos.
Okay, so we'll end it now. Perfect timing.